Guide to the Allen Building Takeover Collection, 1969-2002 UA.31.04.0005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Allen Building Takeover collection
1969-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
UA.31.04.0005
1 Linear Feet 1 box
On February 13, 1969, Duke University students in the Afro-American Society occupied the the main administration building to bring attention to the needs of Black students. These needs included an African American studies department, a Black student union, and increased enrollment and financial support for Black students. This and subsequent events became known as the Allen Building Takeover. The Allen Building Takeover Collection contains announcements; flyers; publications; correspondence; handouts; reports; transcripts; ephemera; clippings; a bibliography; photographs documenting Black Culture Week (Feb. 4-12, 1969) and the Allen Building Takeover (Feb. 13, 1969); and items related to student demands, statements by Provost Marcus Hobbs and by Duke President Douglas Knight, student convocations and demonstrations both in support of and against the Takeover, and later events on the Duke campus and in Durham, N.C. In addition, the collection contains clippings and artwork related to remembering the Takeover, including the 2002 Allen Building lock-in.
Provenance
The Allen Building Takeover Collection was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973-2002, and as a gift in 2019.
Historical Note
On the morning of February 13, 1969, between 50 and 75 black students entered the Allen Building and proceeded to barricade and occupy it. They renamed the building the Malcolm X Liberation School. The students issued a list of demands to the administration, [which included an accredited African-American Studies Department, a black dorm, a black student union, an increase in enrollment and financial support for black students, protection from police harassment, and better working conditions for non-academic staff of the University]. Provost Marcus Hobbs read a statement to the students at about 3:30 PM, urging them to leave the building within one hour to begin a peaceful discussion of the issues. Sometime after 5 o'clock, after a warning from Provost Hobbs that they would face legal ramifications for staying, the students decided to exit. Although the exit was peaceful, a large crowd of mostly white students had gathered outside the building during the day, and this crowd and the police became entangled. The police fired tear gas on the students.
Immediately following the police action, students met to discuss how to proceed. Many students and faculty were upset by the administration's support of the police action; other students and faculty felt that the takeover of the Allen Building was lawless and disruptive. Those who supported the Takeover called for a three day strike on campus and offered alternative classes. Students opposed to the Takeover urged fellow students to attend classes as normal. The administration attempted to calm the campus and address some of the demands posed by the Takeover participants. President Knight addressed Duke on the campus radio station, WDBS.
Afro-American Society and administration members met several times to begin forming an African-American Studies program. The two parties could not reach an agreement on what type of committee should oversee the program. On March 10, a group of students marched to downtown Durham along with students from other colleges to protest the situation. The next day, March 11, 1969, students again went to downtown Durham and marched with other students and Durham residents. The march turned violent, with store windows smashed and other damage to property. The mayor put a curfew on the city for several days.
Dozens of Duke's black students threatened to leave campus following the lack of agreement on the African-American Studies program. They instead planned to attend the Malcolm X Liberation University, a newly-developed school led by community activist Howard Fuller. However, the students soon reversed their decision and decided to remain at Duke University. On March 19, a University Hearing Committee found the students who had occupied the building guilty of violating university regulations. All defendants were sentenced to one year of probation.
[Written by Valerie Gillispie as part of the web exhibit, Campus Protest: Duke University, 1967-1969.]
Collection Overview
The collection features materials documenting the Allen Building Takeover at Duke University. The Subject Files series includes color photographs taken inside the building, announcements, flyers, publications, correspondence, handouts, reports, transcripts, and ephemera relating to Black Culture Week (Feb. 4-12, 1969), the Allen Building Takeover (Feb. 13, 1969), and items relating to student demands, statements by Provost Marcus Hobbs and by Duke President Douglas Knight, student convocations and demonstrations both in support of and against the Takeover, and later events on the Duke campus and in Durham, N.C. Photographs were taken by student participant Lynette Lewis and show the students inside the building during the Takeover; they are accompanied by the original color negatives. Also included are clippings of newspaper and magazine coverage of the Takeover from the campus paper The Chronicle, as well as local, state, and national media.
In addition, the collection contains clippings and artwork related to anniversaries and remembrances of the Takeover. Students created artwork in this collection while participating in the 2002 Allen Building lock-in, an event commemorating 1960s activism at Duke and an opportunity for students and administrators to discuss the racial climate on campus.
Related Materials
Allen Building Takeover Oral History collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
WDBS collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
University Archives Photograph Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access
Original negatives are closed to use.
African American student movements; African American students -- North Carolina -- Durham; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Political activity; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions; African Americans -- North Carolina -- History -- 1964-; Civil rights demonstrations; College students, Black -- North Carolina; Race relations; Student participation in administration; Students -- Political activity; Students, Black -- North Carolina; Color prints (photographs); Color negatives; Photographs; Duke University -- History; Duke University -- Buildings -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Duke University -- Administration; WDBS (Radio station: Durham, N.C.); Duke University. Afro-American Society; Knight, Douglas M., 1921-2005; Hobbs, Marcus E., 1909-
- Subject files, 1969-2002
  Scope and Contents note
  The Subject files series contains a variety of resources relating to the Allen Building Takeover that have been collected by the University Archives staff for teaching and research. These materials are organized into three subseries: Primary documents, Media coverage, and Remembrance. Primary documents include flyers, publications, handouts, correspondence, reports, transcripts, and ephemera. The media coverage subseries features clippings and photocopied clippings from campus, local, state, and national newspapers and magazines. Both of these subseries contain materials from 1969, both during and after the Allen Building Takeover. The third subseries, Remembrance, features clippings relating to the anniversaries of the Takeover in 1989 and 1999, as well as artwork made by participants in the Allen Building Lock-in on April 5-6, 2002.
  Arrangement note
  Ordered by date.
  - Primary source materials relating to the Allen Building Takeover, February 4-19, 1969
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original negatives are closed to use; corresponding prints are in the collection.
    Scope and Contents
    Series contains a wide variety of primary archival sources documenting the Allen Building takeover. Formats include media items, trial and hearing documents, letters, fliers, and photographs.
    - Black Culture Week flyer, Feb. 4-12, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Harambee, Feb. 5, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Documents, Feb. 13, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Documents include The Black Demands, Scenario for Campus Revolt, two requests that students leave the Allen Building peacefully made by Provost Marcus Hobbs, A Co-ordinating Council Response, and other materials.
    - Documents, Feb. 14-19, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Documents include A 3 day boycott of classes -- Friday, Saturday, and Monday ON STRIKE!! Statement by Dr. Douglas Knight for WDBS Radio, Saturday, February 15, 1969, and other materials.
    - Carl Anderson letters,February 15, 1969, March 10,1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Two letters describing the Allen Building Takeover and subsequent events. The letters were written by Oliver Ferguson and Jane Philpott, colleagues of Carl Anderson (1919-2003), a Duke English professor and administrator, who was in Sweden during the Takeover. At the time, Oliver Ferguson was a member of the Duke English department, and Jane Philpott was Acting Dean of the Woman's College.
    - Documents, Feb. 20-28, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Documents include Summary of Action of the Undergraduate Faculty Council and other materials.
    - Documents, March-April 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Documents include Why Black Students Need Student Power...Why Black Students Cannot Get Student Power, memoranda and statements from Duke President Douglas M. Knight, Dilemma at Duke, minutes of the Academic Council, and other materials.
    - Pickets, Protests, and Demonstrations Policy Hearing Committee [and related notes],March 19, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      The trial was open to the Duke community, and the names of the students charged were made publicly available. These notes describe these open hearings, but not the private committee deliberations on punishment.
    - Undated items (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Photographs taken inside the Allen Building, 1969 February 13; 11 items Photographic prints (7) and 35 mm color negative strips (4) (Box 1, Folder 19)
      These seven color photographs were taken by Lynette Lewis Allston inside the Allen Building during the Allen Building Takeover. Photographs depict the student participants sitting and standing inside offices and hallways. Individuals were identified by Lynette Lewis Allston.
      All photographs are 3.5" square, color prints. Accompanied by the original color negatives in 35mm strip format (4 strips cpntaining 7 frames).
      Original negatives are closed to use; please use photographic prints.
      - Photograph of Steph McLeod, George DePriest, Ted Williams, and Ed White inside Allen Building, February 13, 1969 (Box 1, Image UA3104005-P-0001)
      - Photograph of Carolyn Day, Josie Claiborne, CB Claiborne, and Leonard Brown inside Allen Building. Carolyn Day standing on table to look out window above a closed door, February 13, 1969 (Box 1, Image UA3104005-P-0002)
      - Photograph of Chuck Hopkins (on phone at desk), CB Claiborne (at desk), Bertie Howard (seated on chair), Cheri Riley, unidentifed person (seated on desk), Charles Becton, and Clarence Morgan inside Allen Building, February 13, 1969 (Box 1, Image UA3104005-P-0003)
      - Photograph of Sandy Pearsons, Robert Hines, and Lynette Lewis inside Allen Building, February 13, 1969 (Box 1, Image UA3104005-P-0004)
      - Photograph of William Turner inside Allen Building, February 13, 1969 (Box 1, Image UA3104005-P-0005)
      - Photograph of Tony Axam and Catherine Watson inside Allen Building, February 13, 1969 (Box 1, Image UA3104005-P-0006)
      - Photograph of Catherine Watson, William Turner, unidentified person in background, and Cheryl Smith inside Allen Building, February 13, 1969 (Box 1, Image UA3104005-P-0007)
      - Color film negatives (7 frames), 1969 February 13; 4 items 4 35mm strips containing 7 frames (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Media coverage, Jan. 1969-Oct. 1969
    - Chronicle coverage, Jan. 10,1969-March 14, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Durham newspapers, Feb. 9,1969-April 2, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - State and national press, Feb. 1969-Oct.1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Remembrance, 1975-2002
    - Chronicle remembrance, 1975, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Allen Building Takeover: Thirty Years Later, a supplement to The Chronicle, February 12, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Police, crowdclashed in '69: Black students' list of demands in pivotalyear still on the table, The HeraldSun, Feb. 14, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Allen Building Lock-in, April 5-6, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Note: One poster and one collage from 2002 Allen Building Lock-in stored in MC 8.
  - Chronology, undated; Subject Guide and Bibliography, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Malcolm X University, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Account of the Events of February 13-March 19, by Harry Jackson, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)